Hi, today we're going to talk about a technology that you might be using every day, but it's a little bit mysterious.
嗨，今天我們要談論一項你可能每天都在使用的技術，但它有點神祕。
That is,生成式AI.
那就是生成式 AI。
We don't just talk about what chat GPT tools can do for us.
我們不只談論 ChatGPT 工具能為我們做什麼。
What's more important is that we have to open its engine cover together to see what's working inside.
更重要的是，我們必須一起打開它的引擎蓋，看看裡面在運作什麼。
That's right, you might have used it to write an email, think of ideas for you, or even make a report.
沒錯，你可能用過它來寫電子郵件、為你想點子，甚至製作報告。
But have you ever stopped and thought about what magic happened in the black box after you typed a line and pressed send?
但你是否曾停下來思考過，在你輸入一行文字並按下發送後，黑盒子內發生了什麼魔法？
This is where we're going to explore today.
這就是我們今天要探索的地方。
Okay, let's start with the most fundamental question.
好的，讓我們從最基礎的問題開始。
What is生成式AI?
什麼是生成式 AI？
If we can only use one word to describe it, it's definitely creation.
如果我們只能用一個詞來形容它，那肯定就是創造。
It's the most different thing from the traditional AI we used to know.
它最不同於我們過去所知的傳統 AI。
It's the ability to create new things without any middle ground.
它是無需任何中介就能創造新事物的能力。
Look, this picture explains it very clearly.
看，這張圖表解釋得非常清楚。
Traditional AI is more like your garbage email filter.
傳統 AI 更像是你的垃圾郵件過濾器。
Its job is to analyze a letter and then judge where to classify it.
它的工作是分析一封信，然後判斷將它分類到哪裡。
But生成式AI is different.
但生成式 AI 是不同的。
It can directly help you create a new letter.
它可以直接幫助你創造一封新信。
One is analysis, one is creation.
一個是分析，一個是創造。
This is a huge difference.
這是一個巨大的差別。
Okay, here's the question.
好的，問題來了。
How did such an amazing thing come about?
這麼了不起的東西是如何產生的？
It didn't come out of nowhere.
它不是憑空出現的。
It's actually the three key elements.
實際上，它是三個關鍵要素。
At the right time, they all come together to create this innovative, perfect storm.
在恰當的時刻，它們全部匯聚在一起，創造了這場創新的完美風暴。
The first element is that the algorithm has made a big breakthrough.
第一個要素是演算法取得了巨大突破。
Although the concept of AI has been around for a long time,
雖然 AI 的概念已經存在很久了，
in 2017, a structure called Transformer was launched.
但在 2017 年，一個叫做 Transformer 的架構被推出。
Wow, the rules of the game have changed.
哇，遊戲規則改變了。
You can imagine it as a super ability for AI to read up and down.
你可以將它想像為 AI 上下文連貫閱讀的超級能力。
When it's reading a long article,
當它在閱讀一篇長文章時，
it won't forget what it's saying at the end.
它不會忘記在結尾說的是什麼。
The second element is the amount of information.
第二個要素是資訊量。
Think about how many websites, articles, and city codes
想想有多少網站、文章和城市代碼
have become the best fuel for training AI.
已經成為訓練 AI 的最佳燃料。
This is like giving AI the last 100 books in the world
這就像給 AI 世界上最後的 100 本書
so that it can learn all the knowledge and language models from inside.
讓它能學習其中的所有知識和語言模型。
The last element is of course to have a super powerful computer to run.
最後一個要素當然是要有超級強大的電腦來運行。
Like GPU, TPU, these chips designed specifically for AI
像 GPU、TPU，這些專為 AI 設計的晶片
provide a very amazing computing power.
提供了非常驚人的運算能力。
With these magical weapons,
有了這些魔法武器，
we may be able to use so much information
我們或許能夠使用這麼多的資訊
to train these large and incredible models.
來訓練這些龐大且令人難以置信的模型。
I didn't even dare to think about it a few years ago.
幾年前我甚至不敢想像這一點。
When these three things, super powerful computing power,
當這三樣東西──超級強大的運算能力、
large amount of information, and huge computing power
大量的資訊和龐大的計算能力
are all put together and the scale is getting bigger and bigger,
全部結合在一起，規模不斷擴大時，
scientists found a very magical phenomenon called the scale rule.
科學家們發現了一種非常神奇的現象，稱為規模法則。
They found that models not only became more and more intelligent,
他們發現模型不僅變得越來越聰慧，
but even suddenly learned some new skills
甚至突然學到了一些全新的技能
that we have never clearly taught them.
是我們從未明確教過它們的。
For example, like humans, we can step by step analyze problems.
例如，就像人類一樣，我們可以一步步分析問題。
Okay, we know the secret to their success.
好的，我們已經知道了它們成功的秘訣。
So how did they learn it?
那麼它們是如何學會的呢？
In fact, we can simplify this very complicated process
實際上，我們可以將這個非常複雜的過程簡化
into two very important steps.
為兩個非常重要的步驟。
These two steps are pre-training and maintenance.
這兩個步驟是預訓練和微調。
Simply put, the pre-training stage
簡單來說，預訓練階段
is to let models learn the various rules and modes of language first
是讓模型先學習語言的各種規則和模式
and then in the maintenance stage,
然後在微調階段，
we teach them how to become a helpful and useful helper to humans.
我們教導它們如何成為人類有用且有幫助的助手。
In pre-training, you can imagine that AI
在預訓練中，你可以想像 AI
is like reading all the words that can be found on the entire network.
就像閱讀整個網路上能找到的所有文字。
But its purpose is not to die by the knowledge in it.
但它的目的並不是死記其中的知識。
No.
不是。
It is to learn how words are connected between words and words.
它是學習詞與詞之間如何相互連接。
In the brain, we build a super complicated language map.
在大腦中，我們構建了一個超級複雜的語言地圖。
The model after pre-training is a bit like a genius
預訓練後的模型有點像一個天才
who is very smart but does not understand human affairs.
非常聰明但不懂人類事務。
So the maintenance stage is very important.
所以微調階段非常重要。
We will use a lot of artificial feedback to teach it,
我們將使用大量的人工反饋來教導它，
to build it,
來建構它，
to tell it what kind of answer is good and helpful,
告訴它什麼樣的答案是好的且有幫助的，
what kind of answer is not good,
什麼樣的答案不好，
to make it more in line with our expectations.
使其更符合我們的期望。
OK.
好的。
So far, we have probably understood its basic principles.
到目前為止，我們大概已經理解了它的基本原理。
Now, let's think in a more interesting way.
現在，讓我們以一個更有趣的方式來思考。
Let's imagine it as
讓我們把它想像成
a new colleague with a super talented and brilliant company.
一位才華超群、才華洋溢的新同事。
Let's help this AI colleague
讓我們幫助這位 AI 同事
do a performance evaluation
進行績效評估
to see where his strengths and weaknesses are.
看看他的優點和缺點在哪裡。
OK.
好的。
Let's take a look at this new colleague's performance report.
讓我們看看這位新同事的績效報告。
You see, his advantages are obvious.
你看，他的優勢是顯而易見的。
He has a strong language ability,
他具有很強的語言能力，
can do any task a little,
能做任何任務都能稍微涉獵一些，
can remember the content of our chat,
能記住我們聊天的內容，
and even can use external tools.
甚至還能使用外部工具。
But he also has some
但他也有一些
places that need us to take care of.
需要我們照顧的地方。
For example, his knowledge has a deadline.
例如，他的知識有一個時間期限。
Sometimes it will be a serious nonsense.
有時候會說一些很嚴重的胡話。
We call it a hallucination,
我們稱之為幻覺，
and his short-term memory is also limited.
而且他的短期記憶也是有限的。
Let's take a look at it one by one.
讓我們一個接一個地看一下。
Speaking of his advantages,
說到他的優勢，
he has a really strong language ability.
他確實具有非常強的語言能力。
He can help you write a letter,
他可以幫你寫一封信，
do a report analysis,
做一份報告分析，
and even talk to you about literature and poetry in the last second.
甚至在上一秒可以和你討論文學和詩歌。
In the next second, he can switch to explain complex scientific concepts.
下一秒，他可以轉向解釋複雜的科學概念。
What's even better is that
更棒的是
he can remember the text of your conversation,
他能記住你們對話的文本，
just like chatting with real people.
就像和真人聊天一樣。
Even now, many models can still connect to the Internet
現在，許多模型甚至還能連接互聯網
to check the latest information.
來查詢最新信息。
But he has the biggest problem,
但他有一個最大的問題，
which is the hallucination we just mentioned.
就是我們剛才提到的幻覺。
This sentence is super close.
這句話非常恰當。
Imagine that your friend tells you something
想像一下你的朋友告訴你什麼事
in a very certain tone,
語氣非常肯定，
and the details inside are completely wrong.
但裡面的細節完全是錯的。
AI is sometimes like this.
AI 有時候就是這樣。
This also reminds us of one of the most important things.
這也提醒我們一件最重要的事。
What he said is that
那就是
you must not collect 100% of the bill,
你一定不能100%相信它說的，
you must check it.
你必須檢查它。
Another big limit
另一個很大的限制
is the date of his knowledge.
是他的知識的時間期限。
This is like
這就像
a person from a specific day
某個特定日期的人
went to the mountains to practice,
去山裡修行，
completely disconnected from the outside world.
完全與外界隔絕。
So if all the news events that happened that day
所以如果那天發生的所有新聞事件
are not checked by external tools,
都沒有通過外部工具檢查，
he is not worth it.
他就不值得。
Okay, after understanding the advantages and disadvantages of this new colleague,
好的，在了解了這位新同事的優缺點後，
you should have also found that
你應該也發現了
now the focus is not on who is better with AI,
現在的焦點不在於誰比AI更強，
but on how people cooperate with AI
而在於人如何與AI合作
to become a super team of human and AI.
成為人類與AI的超級團隊。
You see, this picture is very clear.
你看，這張圖很清楚。
We humans are strong in critical thinking,
我們人類在批判性思維方面很強，
value judgment,
價值判斷，
and the creativity of the sky and the sky.
以及天馬行空的創意。
What about AI?
那AI呢？
It is strong in the speed of comparison
它在比較速度方面很強
and the ability to handle a lot of information.
以及處理大量資訊的能力。
Think about it,
想想看，
when we combine the advantages of these two sides,
當我們結合這兩方的優勢時，
what kind of combination will it be?
會是什麼樣的組合呢？
So today we start with a mysterious black box
所以今天我們從一個神秘的黑箱開始
and explore all the way,
一路探索，
until we finally see it as a new colleague
直到最後我們把它看作一位新同事
that we are familiar with and a little unfamiliar with.
既熟悉又陌生的同事。
Now the final question
現在最後的問題
actually comes back to us.
實際上回到了我們身上。
AI, this powerful assistant,
AI，這位強大的助手，
is ready to work.
已經準備好工作了。
What about you?
那你呢？
Are you ready to work with him?
你準備好與他一起工作了嗎？